The next set of disorders that we're going to cover are those that can lead to cirrhosis.
Cirrhosis is end-stage liver damage, and it's characterized by disruption of the normal hepatic parenchyma
by these broad bands of fibrosis, and in between the broad bands of fibrosis are regenerative nodules of hepatocytes.
Here's a picture of cirrhosis, and notice that you've got all these little circles of nodular tissue,
and then you can see in between them, these are separated by bands of fibrosis.
And normally, remember that the surface of the liver should be totally smooth,
and so you can clearly see that there's this nodular disruption of the surface of the liver indicative of cirrhosis.
Were you to look at this on microscopic image, what you would see is broad bands of fibrosis, as I'm highlighting here,
which are separating nodules of liver parenchyma.
Again, this is the hallmark of cirrhosis.
And one of the things that's high yield concerning cirrhosis is that the fibrosis is mediated by the stellate cell,
and so this is important because the board examiners will go after it.
The stellate cell can actually secrete TGF-beta, and this is actually the key mediator of that fibrosis.
Recall that the stellate cell lies beneath the endothelial cells that line the sinusoids of the hepatic plates.
When you think about the clinical features of cirrhosis, they're all based on damage to the liver.
For example, one category of clinical findings will be based on portal hypertension.
Because there will be portal hypertension, all of the organs that are draining through the portal system will have an increased hydrostatic pressure.
This will lead to ascites, which is fluid in the peritoneal cavity.
It will lead to enlargement of the spleen, which is called congestive splenomegaly.
And that enlarged spleen can actually become hyperactive and begin to consume red cells or platelets,
and that would be called hypersplenism, that is the consumption of red cells and platelets by an enlarged spleen.
In addition, we can see portal systemic shunts, and some examples include esophageal varices, hemorrhoids, and caplet medusae.
All of these are examples of portal systemic shunts because you can't get the blood through the liver.
And a final complication is hepatorenal syndrome.
This is a rapidly developing renal failure in the context or in the face of cirrhosis.
Of course, the liver plays an important role in detoxifying the blood, and if we lose liver function, that role will be decreased.
This will result in mental status changes associated with asterixis and eventually leading to coma.
These mental status changes would be due to increased serum ammonia, and this would be reversible because it is metabolic.
In addition, the liver plays an important role in removing estrogen from the blood,
and so if the liver is not able to do so, we will get signs and symptoms of excess estrogen.
For example, gynecomastia, spider angiometa, and palmar erythema.
All of these are signs and symptoms of excess estrogen.
And finally, we could get jaundice in the context of cirrhosis because of the fact that the liver hepatocytes play an important role in conjugating bilirubin.
Another important manifestation of cirrhosis would arise because of decreased protein synthesis.
For example, the liver plays an important role in making albumin, but if the liver is not functioning, there would be hypoalbuminemia.
Of course, this would also decrease the oncotic pressure of the blood, further leading to edema.
In addition, the liver makes the vast majority of coagulation factors and also plays an important role in activating vitamin K via epoxide reductase,
and so therefore the patients can develop a coagulopathy.
Now, it's important to note that with this coagulopathy, both the PT and the PTT would rise.
However, the PT is used to follow the degree of deficiency.
And the way I remember this is that it's very similar to the warfarin effect.
Of course, warfarin blocks epoxide reductase, and the PT is used to follow the degree of warfarin effect.
And in the same way in coagulopathy, you lose epoxide reductase,
and therefore PT is used to follow the effect of cirrhosis on the status of the coagulation system.
One of the mechanisms by which cirrhosis can develop is alcohol-related liver disease.
Now, alcohol-related liver disease can actually present with three classic patterns of injury.
In each case, there is damage of the hepatic parenchyma due to consumption of alcohol.
The first change that we can see with alcohol is called fatty liver.
Here, we get accumulation of fat within the hepatocytes, which then results in a heavy, greasy liver.
This is reversible and resolves with abstinence.
Here's an image of fatty change within the liver.
Notice all these circular clear spaces indicating that there is fat in the cells.
Here's a gross image of a liver with fatty change, and it appears large and slightly yellow,
and has a greasy or shiny appearance.
Another pathology that can arise with alcohol is called alcoholic hepatitis.
This is direct chemical injury to the hepatocytes by alcohol, and it generally is seen with binge drinking.
Now, the key mediator here is acetylaldehyde, which is a derivative of alcohol, and that's what then damages the hepatocytes.
The key finding in alcoholic hepatitis will be swelling or ballooning of the hepatocytes.
Note the enlargement and the ballooning of these cells with necrosis and acute inflammation,
and one highly characteristic feature called the malary body.
And here I'm circling for you the multiple malary bodies seen in these hepatocytes.
It's high yield to note, for the purposes of board examination, that the malary bodies are damaged intermediate filaments within the hepatocytes.
Board examiners will ask you what the malary bodies contain, and again, those are damaged intermediate filaments within the hepatocytes.
The presentation of alcoholic hepatitis is painful hepatomegaly with elevated liver enzymes.
However, one very high yield point to note is that the AST will be greater than the ALT.
Now, this pattern is a little different than what we would expect to see in most other causes of liver damage.
And the reason is that the AST is actually located in the mitochondria, and alcohol is a mitochondrial poison.
And so when we damage the mitochondria, we preferentially get an increase in the AST.
And again, that's a fairly characteristic marker of alcohol-related damage of the liver.
Alcoholic hepatitis can result in death.
The third possible pattern of damage to the liver in the face of alcohol is cirrhosis.
This is a complication of chronic alcohol-induced liver damage, and it's seen in about 10 to 20% of alcoholics.
Of course, patients with cirrhosis would present with the signs and symptoms that I've covered just a little while ago.
Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease is when you get fatty change, hepatitis, and or cirrhosis.
So these are the three key changes we saw with alcohol.
However, these occur without a known exposure to alcohol.
This is generally associated with obesity, and it's a diagnosis of exclusion.
That is that you sort of make the assumption that alcohol must be involved
until you've absolutely proved that the patient is not abusing alcohol.
One very helpful finding here would be that the ALT would be greater than the AST.
And again, that's because in this particular case, alcohol is not involved.
And you're well aware, as I just mentioned, that the AST is a mitochondrial enzyme
and is preferentially increased when there is alcohol-based damage.
Hemochromatosis is another disorder that can lead to cirrhosis.
And in hemochromatosis, we get excess body iron that deposits in tissues and then damages organs.
The deposition in tissues is called hemociderosis,
and when it actually damages the tissues, we call that hemochromatosis.
Now, very high yield to note, the damage is actually caused by the generation of free radicals.
Recall that iron has the ability, via the Fenton reaction, to cause the formation of free radicals.
And so when you get excess iron within the tissues, you'll get generation of free radicals,
and that's what mediates the damage in this particular disorder.
Now, it's important to note that hemochromatosis can be primary or secondary.
Let's go back and review a little bit of biochemistry in order to understand this distinction.
Recall that the enterocyte in the duodenum takes up iron from the lumen of the gut.
Now, the enterocyte will basically take up almost all the iron that is present within the gut.
However, the enterocyte will hold on to it and will not pass it off into the blood
unless there is a need within the blood.
So basically, the enterocyte has the ability to detect whether or not iron is necessary
and will only pass the iron off into the blood when iron is required.
Now, that's important because this is the key regulatory step in the human body for iron.
Remember that the human body has no way of getting rid of iron.
Yes, the female can lose a little bit in her menstrual cycle,
and yes, we do lose a little bit by the sloughing of our skin.
However, for all practical purposes, there is no real way to get rid of iron.
And so the regulatory role of the enterocyte is extremely important.
Now, what happens in primary hemochromatosis is that dysregulation gets disrupted
so that whatever comes into the enterocyte goes directly into the blood.
That, of course, is going to result in a massive iron overload,
which is going to deposit in tissues as hemosiderosis
and eventually will damage the tissues, resulting in hemochromatosis.
And so this is the basic pathogenesis of primary hemochromatosis.
Now, it's important to note that in primary hemochromatosis,
the reason why this enterocyte dysregulation occurs
is because you have mutations in a gene called the HFE gene.
And the most common mutation is called C282Y.
Another way by which we can get hemochromatosis is secondary hemochromatosis.
In this particular case, hemochromatosis arises as a complication of transfusions.
Remember that every time we give a transfusion,
the red blood cells are only going to last for a maximum 120 days.
Now, those red blood cells will be turned over,
and when the hemoglobin in the cells is turned over, the iron will be recycled.
And then there is no way to get rid of that iron, as I've just mentioned earlier.
So every bag of blood is basically a bag of iron.
Eventually, all of that iron will build up in the tissues, causing hemochromatosis,
and eventually the organs will get damaged, resulting in hemochromatosis.
This disorder usually presents in late adulthood
because it takes time for the iron to build up and damage the tissues.
And the classic triad is cirrhosis, secondary diabetes, and bronze skin.
Now, basically what's happening here is that as iron deposits in these tissues,
you get end-stage damage, which then destroys the tissues.
So, again, cirrhosis would be end-stage liver damage.
You get damage to the islets, resulting in secondary diabetes mellitus.
This is also called bronze diabetes because the pancreas has a bronze color on gross exam.
And then you get bronzing of the skin because iron can deposit in the skin.
Additional findings are cardiac arrhythmia, if the iron deposits in the heart,
and gonadal dysfunction because iron can also deposit within the testicle,
resulting in testicular atrophy.
Now, the lab findings are going to be based on an iron-overloaded state.
So, because the tissues are loaded with iron and you have tremendous iron stores,
the ferritin will be high.
Of course, any time the ferritin is high, the TIBC is also low.
Much of that iron will actually leak out into the blood,
giving you a high serum iron with a high percent saturation.
And so these are the key lab findings in hemochromatosis.
When you suspect hemochromatosis, you'll perform a biopsy, usually of the liver,
and you'll see a brown pigment within the hepatocytes.
Now, again, remember that when you have a brown pigment in the hepatocytes,
there's a couple things that it could be.
For example, the brown pigment could be lipofuscin,
which is a wear-and-tear pigment that would be present within the liver cells.
It could also be iron from hemochromatosis.
And so one way by which we can make the distinction is to do a special stain called a Prussian blue stain.
The Prussian blue stain will turn iron blue but will not mark the lipofuscin,
i.e. the lipofuscin will remain brown.
Here's a picture of hemochromatosis,
and you can clearly see the brown pigment piling up within the hepatocytes.
Now, again, in order to prove that this brown pigment is iron,
we can do a Prussian blue stain, and the iron would turn blue.
Just for comparative purposes, and because examiners like to go after it,
this is a picture of lipofuscin within the hepatocytes.
Notice that it is also a brown pigment,
and this is a wear-and-tear pigment that is derived from the breakdown of peroxidized lipids.
This pigment piles up in the lysosomes and is just basically a sign that the cells have aged.
It's sort of like the gray hair of the cells,
so that when you see lipofuscin, you know that the cell is old
and has been around for a very long period of time.
Patients who have hemochromatosis can be treated by phlebotomy.
The idea here is to remove red cells,
and of course red cells contain iron, which would decrease the iron load.
Also important to note, there's an increased risk of hepatocellular carcinoma.
Again, that's because the iron will generate all these free radicals,
can damage DNA, which would then increase the risk of potential mutations
to form hepatocellular or liver carcinoma.
Wilson's disease is another disorder that can result in cirrhosis.
It's an autosomal recessive defect in the ATP-mediated hepatocyte copper transport system.
This results in an inability to put copper into bile,
and it also results in an inability to incorporate copper into ceruloplasmin,
which is the key molecule that carries copper around in the blood.
As a result, because you can't put copper into the bile,
copper will build up in the hepatocytes.
It will then leak into the serum and eventually deposit in tissues.
Now copper, just like iron, has the ability to induce free radical damage,
and so hydroxyl free radicals will be produced,
which will then lead to tissue damage.
This disease presents in childhood and manifests as cirrhosis.
Patients can also have neurologic manifestations.
Now among the neurologic manifestations includes behavioral changes,
dementia, chorea, Parkinson-like symptoms, etc.
And so this can mimic many of the other disorders that we'll study
when we learn about neurodegenerative disease.
So for example, if a child has Parkinson's-like symptoms,
we might think about Wilson's disease.
Similarly, dementia or chorea,
which you might normally associate with Huntington's disease, for example,
you might want to think about Wilson's disease as another possibility.
There's also deposition of copper within the cornea,
resulting in Kaiser-Flesher rings.
Of course, because there's going to be a generation of free radicals by the copper,
there'll be an increased risk of hepatocellular carcinoma.
The treatment here is D-penicillamine,
which is basically a copper chelating agent.
Now on laboratory exam, there will be an increased urinary copper.
Some of the copper in the serum will actually leak out into the urine.
There'll be decreased serum ceruloplasmin.
Again, we don't have the ability to put copper into ceruloplasmin,
and so therefore, we won't have as much ceruloplasmin floating around within the blood.
And finally, there'll be increased copper on liver biopsy
because copper can't be put into the bile.
Primary biliary cirrhosis is an autoimmune disease
in which you get granulominus destruction of the intrahepatic bile ducts.
This is classically seen in women.
The average age is 40,
and it can be associated with other autoimmune diseases.
But that's nothing special
because almost every autoimmune disease can be associated with other autoimmune diseases.
We don't know the etiology,
but we do know that there's an antimitylchondrial antibody that's present in the serum,
and that helps to mark the disease.
And that's very high yield for the purposes of examinations.
The patients present with obstructive jaundice,
and that's because you're knocking out the bile ducts.
And cirrhosis is a late complication.
With all that obstruction,
eventually you get liver damage,
which can then lead to cirrhosis,
and hence the name primary biliary cirrhosis.
Primary sclerosing cholangitis is a disorder
in which you get inflammation and fibrosis
of the intrahepatic and extrahepatic bile ducts.
This results in perioductal fibrosis
with a classic onion skin appearance.
Here's an image highlighting the perioductal fibrosis.
Notice that you've got all this fibrosis
wrapping around this bile duct,
and you can clearly see it's associated with inflammation.
And so the characteristic is perioductal fibrosis
with an onion skin appearance.
What you would see if this was the duct
is that you would have fibrosis,
and then fibrosis here,
and the regions in between would appear slightly dilated.
And so what this creates
is sort of a string of pearl appearance,
where this is a pearl,
and this is the string in between the pearl,
and this is again the pearl,
with the fibrosed areas representing the string
in between the pearl.
The etiology of this disorder is unknown,
but it's very high yield to note,
especially for board exams,
that it's associated with ulcerative colitis,
and also that the P anca can be positive.
But you're well aware of the fact
that patients with ulcerative colitis
can also have a P anca,
so that shouldn't be too hard to remember.
Patients classically present with obstructive jaundice,
and again, that's because they're blocking the bile duct,
and so they're going to get the classic signs and symptoms
that we've discussed previously.
Cirrhosis is a late complication,
and there's an increased risk for cholangiocarcinoma,
which is cancer of the bile ducts.
Rice syndrome is fulminant liver failure
and encephalopathy in a child
who has a viral illness and then takes aspirin.
We don't know what causes it,
but we do know of the association.
In fact, if you purchase any bottle of aspirin
and read the back label,
it'll clearly say do not give aspirin
to a child with a viral illness.
We don't fully understand the mechanism of this disorder.
However, we do know that there is mitochondrial damage
of the hepatocytes,
and perhaps that plays an important role.
Again, high yield to know that there is mitochondrial damage
of the hepatocytes.
These patients present with hypoglycemia,
markedly elevated liver enzymes,
and nausea with vomiting,
and it can progress to coma and death.
Now, I should make a note here.
You generally never give a child
with a viral illness aspirin.
However, remember that there is one disease
that can sort of look like a viral illness,
but would require that you give the patient aspirin.
Do you recall that disease?
The answer is Kawasaki syndrome,
which is a vasculitis that preferentially involves
the coronary arteries and presents with signs and symptoms
like conjunctivitis and fever, etc.,
that mimic a viral illness.
And again, that's high yield for board examinations.
Moving on to liver tumors,
hepatic adenoma is a benign tumor of hepatocytes.
Very high yield association
is that it is related to oral contraceptive use
and that it will regress upon cessation
of the oral contraceptives.
Now, although this is a benign tumor,
there is a feared complication that it can rupture,
resulting in intraperitoneal hemorrhage,
especially during pregnancy
when there's high levels of estrogen,
which can drive the growth of this tumor.
Now, again, the reason why there's a risk of rupture
is because the tumors are subcaptular,
right underneath the capsule of the liver,
and so they can rupture through the capsule
and then cause intraperitoneal hemorrhage.
The risk factors for hepatocellular carcinoma
include chronic hepatitis.
So, for example, hepatitis B virus and hepatitis C virus,
both of which can result in chronic hepatitis,
can increase the risk for hepatocellular carcinoma.
In addition, any cause of cirrhosis
is a risk factor for hepatocellular carcinoma.
For example, non-alcoholic fatty liver disease,
hemochromatosis, Wilson's disease,
alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency, etc.
All of these are important causes of cirrhosis.
Finally, one super high yield risk factor
is aflatoxins derived from aspergillus.
Recall from our lecture in the neoplasia chapter
that I told you that in some countries of the world,
there is a very high incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma
due to this mechanism.
Now, in those countries,
they store grains for extended periods of time,
and aspergillus tends to grow on those grains.
It then releases aflatoxins,
which when consumed,
result in an increased risk for hepatocellular carcinoma.
Very high yield for board examinations.
The aflatoxins actually induce P53 mutations,
and that's the mechanism
by which hepatocellular carcinoma will arise.
Hepatocellular carcinoma loves to invade the hepatic vein,
and any time you invade the hepatic vein,
that increases the risk for a syndrome
called Bud Chiari syndrome.
The idea here is that if this is the liver,
recall that you've got a portal vein going into the liver,
and then you've got a hepatic vein coming out of the liver.
In Bud Chiari syndrome,
you get thrombosis of the hepatic vein,
which can then result in painful hepatosplenomegaly,
ascites,
and eventual necrosis of the liver with death.
Now, among the causes of Bud Chiari,
one is hepatocellular carcinoma,
and that's because if hepatocellular carcinoma
is growing within the liver,
it has a propensity to involve the hepatic vein,
which could then result in thrombosis.
Of course, this would present
with painful hepatomegaly and ascites
and could potentially lead to death.
Hepatocellular carcinoma has a poor prognosis,
and that's because the tumors are often detected late,
and that's because usually the patients have cirrhosis
or some other problem in the liver,
and that masks the symptoms
of the hepatocellular carcinoma.
One of the serum tumor markers that is useful
for hepatocellular carcinoma is alpha-fetoprotein.
That's important to remember.
The final point I'd like to make concerning liver tumors
is metastasis to the liver.
Metastasis to the liver is more common than primary tumors.
Important sources include colon carcinoma,
pancreatic carcinoma,
and then lung and breast can also spread to the liver.
When you have metastasis,
you're going to get multiple nodules in the liver,
and clinically, this is going to be detected
as a large liver or hepatomegaly
with a nodular free edge of the liver.
When you feel the edge of the liver on physical exam,
you can feel the bumps in the liver
because there are multiple nodules within the liver.
Here's a classic image just highlighting
that you've got multiple nodules within the liver,
and of course, we would feel those nodules
on the free edge of the liver on physical exam.
And that concludes this section as well as the chapter.